Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎收听EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我是Marco。
My name is Catherine.
我是Catherine。
And today we have a delicious lesson all about Chinese food for you.
今天我们为大家准备了一堂关于中国美食的美味课程。
That's right.
没错。
Today we are ordering Chinese food.
今天我们要点中餐。
Now for many of you listeners that are actually Chinese, you may not recognize these dishes
对于很多本身就是中国人的听众来说，你们可能认不出这些菜。
because we are talking about American Chinese food.
因为我们说的是美式中餐。
That's right.
没错。
So long, long ago, people came over to America from mainly Hong Kong.
很久很久以前，人们主要从香港来到美国。
And so a lot of the food we have is kind of more like Hong Kong food.
所以我们很多食物更像是香港菜。
Cantonese food.
粤菜。
But it's also very American.
但它也非常美国化。
So let's take a listen to today's dialogue and find out exactly what we're eating.
那么，让我们听听今天的对话，看看我们到底在吃什么。
Hi, welcome to Happy Buddha.
你好，欢迎光临快乐佛。
Can I get you anything to drink?
需要给您拿点什么喝的吗？
Coke for me, please.
我要可乐。
I'll have a Sprite.
我要雪碧。
Okay, I'll go get that for you.
好的，我去给您拿。
Are there any questions with the menu?
菜单有什么问题吗？
Do you use MSG?
你们用味精吗？
No ma'am, we are MSG free.
没有，女士，我们不用味精。
Oh man, I haven't had Chinese food in so long.
天哪，我好久没吃中餐了。
I want everything.
我什么都想点。
This place has the best sesame chicken.
这家店的芝麻鸡最好吃。
Yeah, I've been craving Chinese for such a long time.
是啊，我馋中餐好久了。
I used to get takeout all the time.
我以前经常叫外卖。
It's definitely been a while.
确实有一阵子了。
Let's start off with some crab Rangoon.
我们先点一些蟹角吧。
Oh yeah, that sounds good.
哦，听起来不错。
I think I'm going to get the sesame chicken with fried rice, a spring roll and egg drop
我想点芝麻鸡配炒饭、一个春卷和蛋花
soup.
汤。
It's so tempting to order everything on the menu.
真想菜单上的每样都点一遍。
It all looks so appetizing.
看起来都那么诱人。
I think I'll get general toast chicken, hot and sour soup, fried wontons and white rice.
我想点左宗棠鸡、酸辣汤、炸馄饨和白米饭。
Aren't you supposed to be on a diet?
你不是应该在节食吗？
You should at least get brown rice.
你至少该点糙米饭。
I don't think so.
我不这么认为。
I hate brown rice and I'm so sick of eating healthy all the time.
我讨厌糙米饭，而且我受够了总是吃健康食品。
I've been eating so much salad, I swear I've forgotten what meat tastes like.
我吃了太多沙拉了，我发誓我都忘了肉是什么味道了。
There's no better remedy than some nice, greasy, calorie laden Chinese food.
没有什么比一些美味、油腻、高热量的中餐更好的了。
I might even get an order of broccoli beef.
我甚至可能点一份西兰花牛肉。
Oh gosh, I'm so hungry.
哦天哪，我好饿。
Let's call the waitress over.
我们把服务员叫过来吧。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So obviously everything seems so good.
显然每样东西看起来都那么好吃。
Very typical American Chinese dishes and we have a lot of things that we can take a look
非常典型的美式中餐，我们有很多东西可以看看，
at so let's start with language takeaway.
那么我们从语言要点开始吧。
Language takeaway.
语言要点。
In language takeaway today, we're going to be talking about some general food words,
在今天的语言要点中，我们要讨论一些通用的食物词汇，
words that you can use when you're ordering food.
点餐时可以用到的词。
So the first one we should talk about is this MSG.
所以第一个要谈的是这个MSG。
Right, Andrea asks, do you use MSG?
对，Andrea问，你们用味精吗？
So why is she asking this and what is MSG?
所以她为什么问这个，MSG是什么？
MSG is an ingredient in foods.
MSG是食物中的一种成分。
It's kind of like a condiment, something that you put on the food after the food has been
它有点像调味品，是在食物做好后加在上面的东西，
cooked and it makes the food taste better, brighter.
能让食物味道更好、更鲜亮。
It intensifies the flavors a little bit.
它稍微增强一下味道。
Yeah, and it's kind of, it looks like salt or sugar.
是的，它看起来有点像盐或糖。
It's on the tables usually at Chinese restaurants but a lot of people don't like MSG because
在中餐馆的桌子上通常会有，但很多人不喜欢味精，因为
they don't think it's very safe for their bodies.
他们认为味精对身体不安全。
And so actually the waitress says that the food is MSG free, which means there's no MSG
所以实际上女服务员说食物不含味精，意思是里面没有味精。
in it.
是的。
That's right.
没错。
Okay, so she says our food is MSG free, which is this chemical.
好的，所以她说我们的食物不含味精，这是一种化学物质。
I think it's kind of like a chemical that you described.
我觉得这有点像你描述的那种化学物质。
That's right and a lot of people don't want it.
没错，很多人都不想要它。
So you can ask, is this food MSG free?
所以你可以问，这道菜不含味精吗？
You could also ask, is it fat free?
你也可以问，它不含脂肪吗？
Is it salt free?
它不含盐吗？
So this is a very helpful way of asking about what the ingredients are in a dish.
所以这是一种非常有用的方式来询问一道菜的成分。
That's right, that's right.
没错，没错。
And actually Manny is talking about the food as well and he says, yeah, I've been craving
实际上Manny也在谈论食物，他说，是啊，我渴望吃中餐已经很久了。
Chinese for such a long time.
渴望吃中餐已经很久了。
Okay, so the verb here is to crave but he said he's been craving.
好的，这里的动词是渴望，但他说的是他一直在渴望。
So he really has been wanting this food for a long time.
所以他真的很久以来一直想吃这种食物。
So if you say I'm craving Italian food, what does that mean?
所以如果你说我渴望吃意大利菜，那是什么意思？
That means I really want to eat Italian food.
那意味着我非常想吃意大利菜。
You feel like having Italian food.
你想吃意大利菜。
That's right.
没错。
So I'm craving some kind of food.
所以我现在特别想吃某种食物。
I really want to eat it.
我真的很想吃。
Okay.
好的。
And he said that he used to get takeout all the time.
他说他以前经常叫外卖。
So he's obviously talking about Chinese food.
所以他显然是在说中餐。
What does he mean by takeout?
他说的“takeout”是什么意思？
Well, takeout is the opposite of sitting down in a restaurant and eating food.
嗯，“takeout”就是和坐在餐厅里吃饭相反的方式。
Takeout is what you do when you want to go home and eat it.
“Takeout”是你想回家吃的时候做的事。
So in many restaurants, you can order the food and you go and you pick up the food and
所以在很多餐厅，你可以点餐，然后去取餐，
you bring it home.
带回家吃。
Okay, so that's takeout.
好的，那就是外卖。
So it's a noun.
所以它是一个名词。
You get takeout.
你叫外卖。
Right, but it's a little bit different from a different kind of takeout.
对，但它和另一种外卖有点不同。
There's takeout where you order the food and you pick it up and you bring it home.
有一种外卖是你点餐后自己去取，然后带回家。
But there's also delivery and delivery is when you order the food and someone else brings
但还有一种是送餐，送餐是你点餐后别人把食物
it to you.
送到你手上。
So be careful with those two.
所以要注意区分这两者。
All right, very good.
好的，非常好。
Moving forward, Manny kept talking about the food and said, wow, everything on the menu
继续往下，Manny 继续谈论食物，说，哇，菜单上的每样东西
looks so appetizing.
看起来都那么诱人。
It all looks so appetizing.
全都看起来那么诱人。
Okay, appetizing is a way to describe something.
好的，“appetizing”是用来描述某样东西的方式。
In this case, we're describing food.
在这个例子里，我们在描述食物。
So that's normally how we use the word appetizing.
所以我们通常这样用“appetizing”这个词。
So appetizing basically means that you're excited about eating this food because it
所以“appetizing”基本上意味着你对吃这个食物感到兴奋，因为它
looks like it will be good.
看起来会很好吃。
So what about the word appetizer?
那“appetizer”这个词呢？
Does this have anything to do with it?
它和这个有关系吗？
I think appetizer is something that makes you want to eat more.
我觉得“appetizer”是让你想吃更多的东西。
That's why it's at the beginning of a meal.
这就是为什么它在一顿饭的开头。
You have your appetizer before you have your main course.
你在主菜之前先吃开胃菜。
But the word appetizing means that it's very appealing.
但“appetizing”这个词意思是它非常吸引人。
You really want to eat it.
你真的很想吃。
It looks good.
它看起来不错。
It looks delicious.
它看起来很好吃。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
And Andrea was worried because Manny is ordering so much food.
Andrea 很担心，因为 Manny 点了太多食物。
She asks, aren't you supposed to be on a diet?
她问，你不是应该在节食吗？
Okay, so this is a phrase and I want to remind everyone to keep this phrase in mind.
好的，这是一个短语，我想提醒大家记住这个短语。
You can diet, which is a verb, but in this case, you're on a diet.
你可以“diet”，这是一个动词，但在这个例子里，是“on a diet”。
So it's a noun.
所以它是一个名词。
I'm on a diet.
我在节食。
I'm trying to eat healthily.
我试着健康饮食。
I'm trying to watch the things that I put in my body.
我试着注意我吃进身体里的东西。
So usually if you're on a diet, you don't eat really greasy, fatty, take out Chinese
所以通常如果你在节食，你不会吃很油腻、高脂肪的外卖中餐
food.
。
You eat salads and soups.
你会吃沙拉和汤。
Okay, so you are on a diet.
好的，所以你在节食。
Yes, he's on a diet or I was on a diet, but I stopped.
是的，他在节食，或者我以前在节食，但我停了。
Alright, a lot of great appealing food.
好的，很多很棒、诱人的食物。
Why don't we go and listen to our dialogue again and we'll be back with Language Takeaway
我们不如再去听一遍对话，然后回来继续语言要点
Part 2 where we're going to take a look at the specific American Chinese dishes.
第二部分，我们会看看具体的美式中餐菜肴。
Hi, welcome to Happy Buddha.
嗨，欢迎来到快乐佛。
Can I get you anything to drink?
需要喝点什么吗？
Coke for me, please.
我要可乐。
I'll have a Sprite.
我要雪碧。
Okay, I'll go get that for you.
好的，我去拿给你。
Are there any questions with the menu?
对菜单有什么问题吗？
Do you use MSG?
你们用味精吗？
No ma'am, we are MSG free.
不用，女士，我们不含味精。
Oh man, I haven't had Chinese food in so long.
哦，天哪，我好久没吃中餐了。
I want everything.
我什么都想吃。
This place has the best sesame chicken.
这家店的芝麻鸡最好吃。
Yeah, I've been craving Chinese for such a long time.
是啊，我馋中餐好久了。
I used to get takeout all the time.
我以前经常叫外卖。
It's definitely been a while.
确实有一阵子了。
Let's start off with some crab Rangoon.
我们先来点蟹角吧。
Oh yeah, that sounds good.
哦，好啊，听起来不错。
I think I'm going to get the sesame chicken with fried rice, a spring roll, and egg drop
我想我要芝麻鸡配炒饭、一个春卷和蛋花
soup.
汤。
It's so tempting to order everything on the menu.
把菜单上的每样东西都点一遍太诱人了。
It all looks so appetizing.
全都看起来那么诱人。
I think I'll get general toast chicken, hot and sour soup, fried wontons, and white rice.
我想我要左宗棠鸡、酸辣汤、炸馄饨和白米饭。
Aren't you supposed to be on a diet?
你不是应该在节食吗？
You should at least get brown rice.
你至少应该点糙米饭。
I don't think so.
我不这么认为。
I hate brown rice.
我讨厌糙米饭。
And I'm so sick of eating healthy all the time.
而且我受够了总是健康饮食。
I've been eating so much salad, I swear I've forgotten what meat tastes like.
我吃了太多沙拉，我发誓我都忘了肉是什么味道了。
There's no better remedy than some nice, greasy, calorie-laden Chinese food.
没有什么比一些美味、油腻、高热量的中餐更好的了。
I might even get an order of broccoli beef.
我甚至可能会点一份西兰花牛肉。
Oh gosh, I'm so hungry.
哦天哪，我太饿了。
Let's call the waitress over.
我们把服务员叫过来吧。
All right, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at those delicious American Chinese dishes on Language Takeaway
现在让我们来看看“语言学习”部分那些美味的美式中餐。
Part 2.
第二部分。
Language Takeaway.
语言学习。
And so here we are with a number of delicious and very appetizing dishes.
现在我们在这里介绍一些美味又开胃的菜肴。
These are things that you'll normally find in an American Chinese restaurant.
这些是你在美式中餐馆里通常会找到的东西。
The first one is called crab rangoon.
第一个叫蟹肉仰光。
Okay, so this doesn't sound very Chinese at all.
好吧，这听起来一点也不像中餐。
Now rangoon is actually a city in a country called Myanmar or Burma.
仰光实际上是缅甸的一个城市。
And crab rangoon is a special deep-fried dish that's like, it's like deep-fried dumplings,
蟹肉仰光是一种特制的油炸菜肴，就像油炸饺子一样，
but on the inside there's cream cheese and crab.
但里面是奶油芝士和蟹肉。
Crab meat.
蟹肉。
That's right.
没错。
So it's kind of, as you said, like a dumpling, but inside you have cream cheese and crab.
所以就像你说的，有点像饺子，但里面有奶油芝士和蟹肉。
Right.
对。
All right, very good.
好的，非常好。
Now, they also talked about getting the sesame chicken with fried rice.
现在，他们还提到了点芝麻鸡配炒饭。
Okay, so sesame is a very common ingredient in cultures all over the world.
好的，芝麻在世界各地的文化中都是非常常见的食材。
And sesame is a kind of seed.
芝麻是一种种子。
But some people also use some sesame oil in their cooking.
但有些人也在烹饪中使用芝麻油。
And so these all come from these white, small seeds.
这些都来自这些白色的小种子。
And sesame chicken is a kind of chicken that's cooked with sesame seeds.
芝麻鸡是一种用芝麻烹饪的鸡肉。
Okay, very good.
好的，非常好。
And obviously we know what fried rice is.
显然我们都知道炒饭是什么。
You just take, it's just basically rice in a pan with sometimes a little bit of meat
就是把米饭放在锅里，有时加一点肉
and egg and just fry it all together.
和鸡蛋，然后一起炒。
But what about spring rolls?
那春卷呢？
I think these are one of the typical Chinese dishes that everyone knows.
我觉得这是每个人都知道的典型中餐之一。
And actually it's a Chinese dish as well.
实际上它也是一道中餐。
I love spring rolls, although I've never gotten an American spring roll in China.
我喜欢春卷，尽管我在中国从未吃过美式春卷。
The spring rolls we're talking about here are basically wrappers, these like wonton
我们这里说的春卷基本上是用馄饨皮
wrappers that are stuffed with meat and vegetables.
包着肉和蔬菜。
And they're rolled up so they look like a long roll and they're deep fried.
然后卷起来，看起来像长条，再油炸。
So okay, so spring rolls are, as you said, little rolls with meat and sometimes vegetable
所以春卷就像你说的，是包着肉和蔬菜的小卷。
inside.
里面。
Not really sure why they call it spring roll though.
不过我不太确定为什么叫它春卷。
I don't know either.
我也不知道。
Maybe it has to do with the ingredients, like they're vegetables from the spring.
也许和食材有关，比如它们是春天的蔬菜。
Maybe.
也许吧。
Now, another one that I actually really, really like is this egg drop soup.
现在，另一个我真的很喜欢的菜是蛋花汤。
This is delicious.
这很美味。
This is a very simple soup and when you're cooking it, you break an egg and the egg is
这是一道非常简单的汤，做的时候你打一个鸡蛋，鸡蛋
mixed into the soup.
混入汤里。
So it looks like it's kind of got these yellow pieces floating, but it's a really nice simple
所以看起来像有黄色的小块漂浮着，但这是一道非常不错的简单
soup with egg.
蛋汤。
Okay, and that's what it's called, egg drop soup.
好的，这就是它的名字，蛋花汤。
Now you mentioned the wonton wrappers and they also mentioned fried wontons.
你提到了馄饨皮，他们还提到了炸馄饨。
What are wontons?
馄饨是什么？
Okay, wontons are also known as hundun in mainland China, but this is a special kind
好的，馄饨在中国大陆也叫“馄饨”，但这是一种特殊的
of dumpling.
饺子。
It's got a piece of dough basically that's flattened out and inside there's meat, maybe
它基本上是一块擀平的面团，里面包着肉，可能还有
some vegetables.
一些蔬菜。
And sometimes you eat it in soup, but here we're talking about fried wontons, deep fried
有时你会在汤里吃，但这里我们说的是炸馄饨，油炸
wontons.
馄饨。
So you put them in the deep fryer and they're fried so that they're crunchy and the insides
所以你把它们放进油炸锅里炸，这样它们就变得酥脆，里面
are soft.
是软的。
Actually, this is one of my favorite dishes.
实际上，这是我最喜欢的菜之一。
The original one in China though, as you said, the hundun, because it's like in a soup.
不过在中国，原版的就像你说的，馄饨，因为是在汤里的。
And it's very simple, but you have like dumplings in a soup, but the fried ones are also very,
而且很简单，但就像汤里有饺子，但炸的也非常
very good.
非常好吃。
They are both delicious and this is making me very hungry.
两者都很美味，这让我很饿。
So maybe we should listen to our dialogue again.
所以也许我们应该再听一遍我们的对话。
Hi, welcome to Happy Buddha.
你好，欢迎来到快乐佛。
Can I get you anything to drink?
需要我给你们拿点什么喝的吗？
Coke for me, please.
给我一杯可乐。
I'll have a Sprite.
我要一杯雪碧。
Okay, I'll go get that for you.
好的，我去给你们拿。
Are there any questions with the menu?
菜单有什么问题吗？
Do you use MSG?
你们用味精吗？
No ma'am, we are MSG free.
不用，女士，我们不用味精。
Oh man, I haven't had Chinese food in so long.
哦天哪，我好久没吃中餐了。
I want everything.
我什么都想吃。
This place has the best sesame chicken.
这家店的芝麻鸡最好吃。
Yeah, I've been craving Chinese for such a long time.
是啊，我馋中餐好久了。
I used to get takeout all the time.
我以前经常叫外卖。
It's definitely been a while.
确实有一阵子了。
Let's start off with some crab rangoon.
我们先点一些蟹角吧。
Oh yeah, that sounds good.
哦，听起来不错。
I think I'm going to get the sesame chicken with fried rice, a spring roll and egg drop
我想我要点芝麻鸡配炒饭、一个春卷和蛋花
soup.
汤。
It's so tempting to order everything on the menu.
菜单上的每样东西都想点，太诱人了。
It all looks so appetizing.
看起来都让人胃口大开。
I think I'll get general toast chicken, hot and sour soup, fried wontons and white rice.
我想我要点左宗棠鸡、酸辣汤、炸馄饨和白米饭。
Aren't you supposed to be on a diet?
你不是应该在节食吗？
You should at least get brown rice.
你至少应该点糙米饭。
I don't think so.
我不这么认为。
I hate brown rice and I'm so sick of eating healthy all the time.
我讨厌糙米饭，而且我受够了总是吃健康食品。
I've been eating so much salad, I swear I've forgotten what meat tastes like.
我吃了太多沙拉，我发誓我都忘了肉是什么味道了。
There's no better remedy than some nice, greasy, calorie laden Chinese food.
没有什么比一些油腻、高热量的中餐更好的解药了。
I might even get an order of broccoli beef.
我甚至可能再点一份西兰花牛肉。
Oh gosh, I'm so hungry.
哦天哪，我好饿。
Let's call the waitress over.
我们把服务员叫过来吧。
Alright, we're back.
好了，我们回来了。
As we mentioned, these dishes have a certain American influence to them.
正如我们提到的，这些菜带有一定的美国风味。
They're not really spicy.
它们其实并不辣。
I think that's the main difference as well.
我认为这也是主要区别。
American Chinese food doesn't really have the intense garlic flavor nor is it spicy
美式中餐没有浓烈的蒜味，也不像
like usual Chinese food.
传统中餐那样辣。
That's right.
没错。
I think that part of that is, like I said, due to the fact that a lot of the Chinese
我认为部分原因，就像我说的，是因为很多最早来的华裔
Americans who first came over came from Hong Kong.
美国人来自香港。
And so Hong Kong food is not as famous for its spiciness.
而香港菜并不以辣闻名。
It's not like Sichuan food.
不像四川菜。
You will see a lot of sweet sauces like this general sauce chicken is a very, very sweet
你会看到很多甜酱，比如这个左宗棠鸡的酱汁就非常非常甜。
sauce.
酱汁。
You'll also see a lot of soy sauce in American Chinese cooking.
在美式中餐烹饪中，你也会看到很多酱油。
And so these are flavors that are very, very strong and they're not the same as the Chinese
所以这些味道非常非常浓烈，和你在中国吃到的
peppers and these spicy foods you get in China.
辣椒和辣味食物不一样。
That's right.
没错。
And actually there's one more dish that we didn't mention in the dialogue actually, but
实际上，对话中我们没提到一道菜，但
is very famous all around the United States.
在美国各地非常有名。
It's called chop suey.
它叫炒杂碎。
Chop suey.
炒杂碎。
And many people have argued about where the name comes from.
很多人争论过这个名字的由来。
But chop suey is just basically like everything chopped up and fried together, right?
但炒杂碎基本上就是把所有东西切碎然后一起炒，对吧？
It's like stir fried vegetables and meat.
就像炒蔬菜和肉。
And all put together in just a bowl.
全部放在一个碗里。
Yeah.
是的。
Well, my favorite thing about the American Chinese food that we get is that we get it
嗯，我最喜欢我们吃的美式中餐的一点是，它装在
in these little boxes.
这些小盒子里。
They're very cute.
它们很可爱。
And you take them home and you open them up and every food has a box.
你带回家打开，每样食物都有一个盒子。
And then at the end, you also get a fortune cookie, which is a very small cookie.
最后，你还会得到一个幸运饼干，一个很小的饼干。
And inside there's a piece of paper.
里面有一张纸条。
So don't eat the paper.
所以别吃那张纸。
And the paper has a fortune for you.
纸条上写着你的运势。
It says, you will be very lucky today.
它会说，你今天会很幸运。
Or your favorite number is 17.
或者你最喜欢的数字是17。
And they're very cute.
它们很可爱。
Actually, you can see these boxes that Catherine mentions on our lesson page.
实际上，你可以在我们的课程页面上看到凯瑟琳提到的这些盒子。
It's the lesson photo.
那是课程照片。
And as you said, very, very common.
就像你说的，非常非常常见。
Each dish is put in this little box.
每道菜都放在这个小盒子里。
So if you ever get Chinese food, you'll see people carrying these little boxes around
所以如果你吃中餐，你会看到人们提着这些小盒子到处走，
because they're very convenient and easy to carry.
因为它们非常方便携带。
But the fortune cookie thing is also very common.
但幸运饼干也很常见。
I was actually very surprised when I went to China and there were no fortune cookies.
我去中国时发现没有幸运饼干，真的很惊讶。
It's weird, isn't it?
很奇怪，对吧？
I think it's funny because we expect these things to be very Chinese.
我觉得有趣的是，我们以为这些东西很中国化。
But in fact, when you come to mainland China, they don't have fortune cookies.
但实际上，当你来到中国大陆，他们没有幸运饼干。
So I think it's a nice surprise but also kind of confusing.
所以我觉得这是个惊喜，但也让人有点困惑。
That's right.
没错。
Well, a very interesting topic.
嗯，一个非常有趣的话题。
And in the future, we're going to continue doing different lessons about different cuisines.
未来我们会继续做不同菜系的课程。
We have Italian food coming up sometime soon.
我们很快会推出意大利菜的内容。
So that's going to be very good as well.
那也会非常棒。
And of course, if you have any lesson suggestions or maybe you want to suggest the cuisine from
当然，如果你有任何课程建议，或者想推荐你国家的菜系，
your country, you can visit our website englishpod.com and leave your comments there.
可以访问我们的网站 englishpod.com 并在那里留言。
We hope to see you guys there and until next time.
我们希望能在那见到你们，下次再见。
Bye.
再见。
Thanks for watching.
感谢观看。